If I were to ask you to think of the two
most iconic moments of Barack Obama's
presidency, it's highly likely you'll
either land on this photo or this
moment. Tonight, I can report to the
American people and to the world
that the United States has conducted an
operation that killed Osama bin Laden,
the leader of al-Qaeda. Once upon a
time, the Affordable Care Act might have
also loomed large. Uh or Georgia behind
the camera uh is dead set on the tan
suit being the most iconic moment. But,
it's the military action which has
really stuck across the whole culture.
War is often what we think that leaders
do. There's a phrase which gets thrown
around in British politics a lot that
the first duty of government is the
defense of the realm.
Which, let's be honest, pretty cringe.
You're not King Arthur. You did PPE
Oxford. But, it underlines a cultural
trope in which we are minded to think of
a leader as being more of a leader if
they lead through a conflict. And that
trope is, in many regards, just as
dangerous to the world at the moment as
the more bombastic adventures of Donald
Trump.